Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
- Professional correspondence-subject files
  - UNESCO (United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization)
    - Conferences, additional material relating to the CONFINTEA conferences may be found in the UNESCO: Correspondence files under the relevant date ranges
      - CONFINTEA V, Hamburg, 1997
        - Non-governmental organization (NGO) surveys and reports, 1996; includes survey of member states relating to NGOs (Box 168)
        - Thematic working groups (Box 168)
        - U.S. Department of Education briefing book (Box 168)
        - U.S. Department of Education planning meeting, includes agenda and notes from preparatory meetings (Box 168)
        - U.S. Department of Education final report, final report on conference for US DOE, by Maigenet Shifferaw (Box 168)
        - Miscellaneous, photocopied clippings, lists of documents,. Miscellaneous handouts, etc. (Box 168)
      - CONFINTEA VI, Belem, 2009
        - Adult Education and Development No. 75, 2010; special issue devoted to CONFINTEA (Box 168)
        - Charters reports, 2011; My involvement with six UNESCO International Conferences on Adult Education (presented at conference); Suggestion for CONFINTEAs and the implementation of the Belem Framework for Action (Box 169)
        - Conference material, 2009; 2 folders; schedule, programme, agenda, papers, etc. (Box 169)
        - Follow-up activity, 2010-2011; includes "Reporting template for national progress reports" (Box 169)
        - Mid-term report on conference progress, 2003; Coping with the learning challenges: Between idealism and reductionism (Box 169)
        - Miscellaneous, 2007-2009; statements, announcements, press releases, etc. (Box 169)
      - DPI/NGO, New York, 2002; 55th annual conference (Box 169)
      - Pan-European Conference on Adult Education, Barcelona, 1996; 2 folders; some material in Spanish; includes final published copy of full proceedings, 424pp. (Box 169)
      - UNESCO's World of Education, Washington, DC, 2003 (Box 170)
      - World Conference on Higher Education, Paris, 1998; theme is higher education in the 21st century (Box 170)
    - Crime prevention and control, circa 1988; draft resolution and committee report on prison education (Box 170)
    - Documentation in adult education, 1973; 1977,; 1983,; 1998-2005; includes several reports from the Documentation Centre and Library (new acquisitions, bibliographies) (Box 170)
      See also Adult Learning Documentation and Information Network (ALADIN).
    - Executive Board material, 1965; 1967,; 1974 (Box 170)
    - Institute for Education (UIE), 1990; 1996-1998,; 2004-2005,; 2011; papers, newsletters, reports, programmer for 2004-2005, etc. (Box 170)
    - International Advisory Committee for Out of School Education, 1967-1968; 1970-1971; reports on activities (Box 170)
    - International Bureau of Education (IBE)
      - Newsletter, "Educational Innovation", 1993-1998 (Box 170)
      - Printed material, reports, 1975; 1995,; 1997,; undated; includes final report on International Conference on Education, 35th Session (Box 170)
    - International Committee for the Advancement of Adult Education, 1963; 1965-1966; papers from 1963 meeting in Paris (Box 170)
    - International Education Year (IEY)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 171)
      - Reports, 1970-1971; The United States and International Education Year (1971); Opportunities for business leadership in international education (1971); Education for business leadership in a global society (1970); Business and education for world affairs (1971); Education in the seventies: An agenda for action (undated) (Box 171)
      - A World to Gain: A Handbook for International Education Year, 1969-1970; draft and final printed version (Box 171)
      - Miscellaneous, 1969-1971; printed material from UNESCO and from the U.S. National Commission; text of speech by Alfonso da Silva (1970); "An examination of objectives, needs and priorities in international education in U. S. secondary and elementary school (1969) (Box 171)
    - Japan, See Japanese National Commission for UNESCO.
    - Literacy, 1967; 1969-1971,; 1990,; 1996; 2 folders; includes material from panel for the evaluation of experimental literacy projects; information from Iran; report on literacy 1967-1969; Data collection and analysis: Improving the information base for literacy programmes (1990) (Box 171)
    - Literacy Initiative for Empowerment (LIFE), 2012; report (Box 171)
    - National Commissions
      - Australia, 1961-1964; includes correspondence with Robert Luke, Sandy Liveright, Sidney Raybould; clippings about ANC (Box 171)
      - Canada, 1967 (Box 171)
      - China, 1983 (Box 172)
      - U.S.
        See also UNESCO: International Education Year (IEY).
        - 20th anniversary of UNESCO, 1966 (Box 172)
        - Conference, 10th, Kansas City, 1965; 2 folders; includes ANC's notes, conference material, programs signed by Harry S. Truman and staff of Truman Library (Box 172)
        - Conference, 11th, New Orleans, 1966; 2 folders; includes ANC's notes, conference material, etc. (Box 172)
        - Conference, 13th, San Francisco, 1969 (Box 172)
        - Correspondence, 1964-1967 Sep; 4 folders (Box 172)
        - Correspondence, 1967 Oct-1972; 1979-1980,; 2005,; 2010,; 2012; 6 folders (Box 173)
        - Correspondence, undated (Box 173)
        - Minutes, 1968-1970 (gaps); gaps (Box 173)
        - Printed material, scattered issues of newsletter, clippings, brochures, etc. (Box 173)
        - Miscellaneous reports and papers (Box 173)
    - Network of Networks project, 1997; 1999,; undated; includes list of participants, examples of abstracts, and questionnaire, directory from 1999/2000 (Box 174)
    - Newsletters
      - Adult Education, 1982; 1987,; 1990,; 1993-1994 (Box 174)
      - Americans for the Universality of UNESCO, 1990; 1995-2000,; 2004 (Box 174)
      - The Interdependent, 1997-1998; 2000-2002,; 2004 (Box 174)
      - Miscellaneous, 1965; 1971,; 2003-2004; scattered issues of Connect, Education Today, Literacy, UNESCO Features (Box 174)
    - Non-governmental Organizations (NGOs), 1962; 1967,; 1973-1976; 2 folders; correspondence, lists, U.N. publications, etc. (Box 174)
    - Printed material, miscellaneous, 2 folders; brochures, booklets, fact sheets, etc. about UNESCO in general: what it is, what it does, how it works; includes "A Forum in Restoration: International intellectual cooperation and America's interests in UNESCO" (Box 175)
    - Reports, miscellaneous
      - Caribbean Regional Council for Adult Education (CARCAE), Report of 6th General Assembly, 1999 (Box 175)
      - Long-term outline plan for 1971-1976, circa 1970 (Box 175)
      - Recommendation on the development of adult education, 1976; draft and final (Box 175)
      - Reference points: The four first international conferences on adult education and their political, social, cultural, and educational context, 1997 (Box 175)
      - Report of the Secretary-General on the work of the organization, 1989 (Box 175)
      - Status and trends: Education for all, 1993 (Box 175)
    - Study on the impact of school system on life-long education, 1968-1970; 3 folders; project chaired by ANC; correspondence, drafts, notes (Box 175)
    - Sub-regional training workshop on information supports for adult education, 1981-1983; workshop led by ANC at meeting in Harare, Zimbabwe (Box 176)
      See also Writings: Counselors in Adult and Continuing Education, published edition [Frost ID: ANC 105] which contains a copy of the proceedings; Writings: Information, guidance and counselling services and the selection of appropriate and efficient information supports and resources for adult education
    - Telephone directory, 1973 (Box 176)
    - U.S. withdrawal from
      - Charters on, 1985-1986; two papers by ANC: Observations about UNESCO at the time of the U.S. withdrawal (1985) and UNESCO and the U.S. (1986) (Box 176)
      - Clippings, 1983-1987; includes transcript of on-the-record briefing from Assistant Secretary of State Gregory Newell; clippings from newspapers and magazines (Box 176)
      - Notes, etc., handwritten notes by ANC (Box 176)
    - Zonta Club presentation, See Zonta Club of Syracuse.
    - 20th anniversary, See UNESCO: National Commissions: U.S.: 20th anniversary of UNESCO.
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 176)
  - UNIDROIT, See International Institute for the Unification of Private Law (UNIDROIT).
  - United Community Chest of Onondaga County, 1963-1967; newsletters, annual reports (Box 176)
  - United Nations Association of Central New York (UNA/CNY)
    - Bylaws and purpose (Box 176)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1979; 2 folders (Box 176)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1995; undated (Box 177)
    - Newsletters, 1970-1985; 1988 (Box 177)
    - Printed material (Box 177)
  - United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO), See UNESCO.
  - United Nations University, 1971-1980; undated; includes UNESCO questionnaire on feasibility; paper by Ward Morehouse, "The United Nations University: An intellectual utopia or a bureaucratic morass?"; publications by Harold Taylor and Seth Spaulding; correspondence, newsletters, etc. (Box 177)
  - United States Coalition for Education for All, See Education For All (EFA).
  - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, See United States Department of Education.
  - United States Department of Education, 1967; 1969,; 1972-1977,; 1980,; 1984,; 1991,; 1997,; 2000; 2 folders; includes material on "America 2000" and the 2004 National Assessment of Vocational Education (Box 177)
  - United States Department of State, See Foreign Policy Conference.
  - United States Marine Corps (USMC), See Automated Beverage Control (ABC); Barnes, Albert G..
  - United States National Commission for UNESCO, See UNESCO: National Commissions: U.S.
  - Universidad Autonoma de Guadalajara (Mexico), 1991 (Box 177)
  - Universidad Nacional Experimental Simón Rodríguez, See Simon Rodriguez University.
  - Universidad Simon Rodriguez (USR), See Simon Rodriguez University.
  - Universities and the Quest for Peace, See Transnational Studies Center.
  - University of Alberta, See Campbell, Duncan.
  - University of Botswana, See Youngman, Frank.
  - University of Bradford, See University of Leeds.
  - University of British Columbia, 1938-1941; 1945,; 1948-1953,; 1965-1968,; 1972,; 1976-1977,; 1983-1990,; 2012; 2 folders; ANC's alma mater; includes material relating to him as both student and alumnus, as well as by-laws for UBC Chapter of International House Association (IHA); See also Personal: University of British Columbia, 60th class reunion. (Box 177)
  - University of California Extension, 1961; Academic plan for UC Extension, written by Paul Sheats (Box 177)
  - University of Cambridge (Ottawa, Canada), 1978; inventory of the archives of the Board of Extra-Mural Studies (Box 178)
  - University Central of Venezuela, 1973-1974; relates to masters program in andragogy; Felix Adam, others (Box 178)
  - University of Chicago, 1945-1951; 1956-1957,; 1966,; 1969-1974,; 1994,; 1997,; 2001,; 2003; 4 folders; majority relates to ANC as student and alumnus; includes material relating to International House (IHA), a few items from Cy Houle, list of 1974 doctoral candidates, student directory for 1946-1947 (Box 178)
    See also International Harvester.
  - University Club of Syracuse, 1971; 1977-1981,; 1986-1994,; undated; includes ANC's membership cards; dissolution of club (Box 178)
  - University College, See Syracuse University: University College.
  - University Continuing Education Association (UCEA)
    This organization has had several names. See also National University Extension Association (NUEA), which was the name of the organization from 1915 to 1980; National University Continuing Education Association (NUCEA), which was its name from 1980 to 1996; University Continuing Education Association (UCEA), which was its name from 1996 to 2011; and University Professional and Continuing Education Association (UPCEA), which is its current name..
    - Awards, 1998; 2004; lengthy descriptions of all UCEA awards, both national and regional; clipping about ANC receiving the Julius Nolte Award (Box 178)
    - Correspondence, 1996-2008; 3 folders (Box 178)
    - Correspondence, 2010-2011 (Box 179)
    - Charters notes, undated (Box 179)
    - Conferences
      - Annual, 1997-2011; 15 folders; amount and type of material vary; may include programs, papers, presentations, lists of attendees, awards and honors booklets, maps, agendas, etc. Program from 1999 includes information on renaming of the UCEA Region II Award for Outstanding Continuing Educator New to the Field as the Alexander Charters Award; See also Memorabilia: Photographs: Professional, identified. (Box 179)
      - Region II, 1999; 2004-2005,; 2009; 4 folders (Box 180)
    - Membership directory, 2004 (Box 180)
    - Newsletter, InFocus, 1996-2009; 4 folders; gaps (Box 180)
    - Past presidents, includes "feedback from" emails (Box 180)
      See also Conferences, above; many conference programs include lists of past presidents.
    - Position papers, 1998; 2000-2001; topics include e-education, intellectual property, continuing education CEOs, for-profit universities, more (Box 180)
    - Miscellaneous, includes President's Address (1997), dues schedule, brochures and printed material, printouts of two PowerPoint presentations (Box 180)
  - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (UCEPR)
    - Bylaws (Box 181)
    - Charters interview, undated; transcript of interview of ANC by Jess Burkett (Box 181)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1969; 10 folders; correspondents include Henry G. Alter, Granville Davis, C. Fletcher Scott, Alexander A. (Sandy) Liveright, Carl Tjerandsen (Box 181)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1974; undated (Box 182)
    - History, 1962; certificate of incorporation, 501(c)3, minutes from inaugural meeting, historical background paper, etc. (Box 182)
    - Printed material (Box 182)
    - Proposals, Ford Foundation, 1965; 1972,; undated (Box 182)
    - Proposals, others, U.S. Office of Education; unspecified (Box 182)
    - Reports, position papers, etc., 1961; 1968,; undated; 2 folders (Box 182)
      An approach to the problem of designing a curriculum in education for public responsibility, by Glen Pool (undated); Continuing education as a catalyst, by Granville Davis (undated); Education for public responsibility, University of Oklahoma (1968); Formation of the Ohio Council on Higher Continuing Education, by J. Eugene Weldon (1968); Institute on community service programming, Syracuse University (undated); Metropolis: Creator or destroyer (undated; part of "Values in Conflict" series); Moral basis of international action, by Joseph Cropsey (1961); New technology and human values (undated; outline only); Notes for a film series on Urbanism, by George Stoney (undated); Pennsylvania State University: An organizational concept for a program of public affairs and service (1968); Suggestions for organizational review (undated); untitled group of papers, summary by James B. Whipple (undated); The university and the urban condition, by Nathan Cohen (1968; includes biographical sketch of author)
  - University of Delhi, 1967-1968; Delhi - Oxford - Syracuse University project; A. A. Johnson, Frank Jessup, Ford Foundation (Box 182)
  - University of East London, 2000 (Box 182)
  - University of Georgia, 1952; 1973,; 1978,; 1984,; 1990,; 1993-1997; includes photographs; numerous issues of Junto2000 Gazette newsletter. (Box 182)
    See also JUNTO program.
  - University of Iowa, 1994-1995; catalog for Guided Correspondence Study (Box 183)
  - University of Kansas, 1966; regarding their use of educational television (Lenkurt Electric Co., Inc.) (Box 183)
  - University of Leeds, 1990; report, "Developing wider access to universities," joint project with Leeds and Bradford (Box 183)
  - University of Ljubljana, 1992-1993; report, "Educational sciences undergraduate degree program, revized [sic] curricula" (Box 183)
  - University of Madras, 1995-1996; 2002-2004; invitations for ANC to serve on two examination committees, including abstracts of the dissertations. (Box 183)
    See also Matheswaran, V. P.
  - University of Maryland, See also Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools (MSA); National University Extension Association (NUEA): Project Head Start.
    - Adult Education Staff Development Project, Region III, 1972-1973; first annual report, 221pp. (Box 183)
    - Correspondence, 1954; 1965-1967,; 1971,; 1974-1975,; 1978,; 1990,; undated; includes a few brochures and other printed items (Box 183)
  - University of Minnesota, 1948; 1953-1954,; 1971,; 1976; includes correspondence with Julius Nolte.; See also Wingspread Conference. (Box 183)
  - University of Missouri-St. Louis, 1998; undated; printed material, most relating to telecourses, communication technology for teaching, etc.; includes conference program, "International conference on the social impact of information technologies" (Box 183)
  - University of Montreal / Université de Montréal, 1987; 1991,; 1995; some in French (Box 183)
  - University of New England, 1965-1966; 1971-1972,; 1992-1993; includes course catalog from College of Osteopathic Medicine (Box 183)
  - University of New York, See State University of New York (SUNY), various locations; University of the State of New York.
  - University of Nottingham, 1990-1996; includes several issues of their "Register of research interests" (Box 183)
    See also Pemberton, Clive.
  - University of Oklahoma, 1948; 1977,; 1988,; 1994 (Box 183)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1948; 1974 (Box 183)
    See also Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools (MSA): University of Pennsylvania.
  - University of Phoenix, 1990; 1994; includes one issue (vol. IV, no 1) of "Adult Assessment Forum: Journal of Quality Management in Adult-Centered Education" (Box 183)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1968-1971; bulk is related to ANC's work as member of Board of Visitors; includes correspondence, background material on the university, Board of Visitors reports, printed material (Box 183)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1972-1977; undated; 7 folders; bulk is related to ANC's work as member of Board of Visitors; includes correspondence, background material on the university, Board of Visitors reports, printed material (Box 184)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1968-1974; brochures, faculty guide, issues of student newsletter, catalogs, other assorted printed material (Box 184)
  - University Professional and Continuing Education Association (UPCEA), 2013-2014; relates to 99th annual conference; includes ANC memorabilia (Box 184)
  - University Regent Theater, See Syracuse University: University Regent Theater.
  - University of Saskatchewan, 1948; 1975,; 1978 (Box 184)
  - University of the State of New York
    - Correspondence, 1954; 1965-1967,; 1975-1979 (Box 185)
    - Printed material, 1966-1967; 1974-1977,; 1982,; 1984; directory, position papers, newsletter issues, etc. (Box 185)
    - Public School Adult Education Conference (SUNY), 1966 (Box 185)
  - University of Tennessee, 1974; 1983,; 2002; includes information on their Self-Directed Learning Research Group (Box 185)
  - University of Texas, 1951; 1974 (Box 185)
  - University of Toronto, 1966; includes "Home Study Course Volume 2" on comparative studies in adult education (Box 185)
  - University of Wisconsin, 1948; 1956-1957,; 1972,; 1974,; 1978 (Box 185)
  - University of the World, See Chamberlain, Martin.
  - University of Zambia, 1975 (Box 185)
    See also Bown, Lalage.
  - University of [A-Z] (U.S. universities), Alaska, California, Delaware, etc. (Box 185)
  - University of [A-Z] (non-U.S. universities), alphabetized by country; includes universities in Australia, Colombia, Chile, India, Rhodesia, Scotland, etc. (Box 185)
  - Upper Iowa University, catalog for their external degree program (Box 185)
  - Urban League of Onondaga County
    - Agency self-study, 1967 (Box 185)
    - Bylaws and purpose, 1964 (Box 185)
    - Clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 185)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1965; 3 folders (Box 185)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1970; 2000,; undated; 4 folders (Box 186)
    - Newsletters, 1966-1969; includes other organizations, e.g. National Urban League, Association of Urban Universities, etc. (Box 186)
    - Policy statements and resolutions, 1961-1965; topics include family planning, racial integration, civil rights (Box 186)
    - Printed material (Box 186)
    - Reports, papers, proposals, etc., 1965-1969; 2 folders (Box 186)
      Some are by the Urban League, some by the National Urban League, some by third parties. Titles are: Activity report for the economic development and employment department of the Urban League of Syracuse and Onondaga County (1967); Application for community support (undated); A change of climate, by Melvin R. Goode (speech, 1967); Citizens Housing Center (report, 1969); Crusade for Opportunity: Sequential development of a pre-employment training program (undated); Education committee proposal for conversion of Croton School to an early childhood education center for the west side (1966); A look at the Syracuse Community Development Association (undated); A new thrust for the urban league movement (working paper, 1968); Non-profit housing corporations, by Bernard E. Loshbough and Seymour Baskin (1967); Program for purchase and rehabilitation of housing for resale to low-income purchasers (HUD publication, undated); School district reorganization and school district boundary changes for September 1965 (1965); The university and social responsibility: Interim report, by Syracuse University (1969); Urban league business: An approach to action, by John B. Turner (1966)
  - U, miscellaneous (Box 187)
  - Vanderkamp [Vandercamp], See Personal: Vanderkamp.
  - Varner, Walter E., 1974; 2009 (Box 187)
  - Vaughn, Harold A.
    - Correspondence, 1982-1985; includes copies of c.v. (Box 187)
      See also Syracuse University: Foreign study programs: Correspondence.
    - Writings, 1982-1985; 2010; 2 folders (Box 187)
      Fixed term assignments abroad and other international exchange options, with ANC (1985; drafts and final); International projects and sources of funding: Guidelines for faculty (1982); Proposal to establish a center for international/intercultural programs and studies, with ANC (1984); When Syracuse University established a presence abroad (2010)
  - Venezuela, 1986; 1999,; 2003; most appears to relate to either a conference or seminar held in Caracas, ANC's role unclear; includes ANC's notes, numerous names and addresses, email from Simon Rengifo (Box 187)
  - Verner, Coolie, 1966; 1971-1972,; 1977 (Box 187)
  - Veterans, general, includes proposal to establish an external degree program for veterans at Federal City College, conference on Vietnam Veterans Training, printed material related to veterans' assistance, etc. (Box 187)
  - Video documentary on Alexander Charters, 1990-1993; undated; notes, treatment, budget for project, led by Don Holmwood; unknown if it was ever completed (Box 187)
    See also charters_023 audiorecording.
  - Vincennes University, undated; printed material on their degree completion program (Box 187)
  - Vio, Francisco, See Simon Rodriguez University.
  - V, miscellaneous (Box 187)
  - Wagon Wheel exchange, initiated by R. E. Michael at Ball State University, related to a new course entitled "Management of extension and continuing education systems" (Box 187)
  - Walatara, Douglas, 1982; University of Colombo, Sri Lanka; includes c.v. (Box 187)
  - Walker, Mort, 1972; cartoonist (Box 187)
  - Waller. Ross, 1966; University of Manchester, regarding his visit to Syracuse (Box 187)